A Guide to the Richard Henry Stoddard Collection
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #8456-a
Richard Henry Stoddard Collection 1858-1894
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
8456-a
15 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Deposit [ 17 Dec 1963 ] 20 Feb 1967
Item Listing
- Manuscripts
  - Poem beginning, "The sky is a drinking cup.. .", 1858 Jan 17; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem, " The Canticle of the Sun ", 1894 Jul 31; AMsS, 2 p.
  - Poem, " Birds ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "There are gains for all our losses.. .", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
  - Poem beginning, "There are gains for all our losses.. ", n. d.; AMsS, 1 p.
    [Quotation of first verse of a poem.]
  - Poem, " Epicedium ", n. d.; AMsS, 5 p.
- Letters
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to John G[odfrey] Saxe, Burlington, Vermont, 1851 Nov 2; ALS, 3 p.
    [Yearns to meet him and read his book; says he had many laughs while reading Saxe's book; compliments him on a book which has gone into third edition and which Stoddard has given to a friend traveling in Europe. ]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to John Williamson Palmer, [ Baltimore], [ New York], 1857 Feb 3; ALS, 2 p.
    [Compliments him on his choice of English poems to be published in
    Folk Songs
    predicts that Palmer will easily find a publisher.]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to Thomas Dunn English, [ Philadelphia], 1858 Sep 23; ALS, 1 p.
    [Says he is making himself a small collection of choice autograph poems of American poets; asks him to copy his poem "Ben Bolt."]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to James T. Fields, New York, 1865 Aug 7; ALS
    [Urges him to do something in a literary and financial way for Henry Timrod. ] (tipped in
    The Bryant Festival at the Century
    , 1865)
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to John Williamson Palmer, [ Baltimore, New York], 1866 Jun 25; ALS, 3 p.
    [Lauds
    says his collection of autographs includes one of the best later poems of Elizabeth Barrett Browning from a volume on the Italian war, he has nothing complete of [ William Makepiece] Thackeray or Jean Jungelton and he could find manuscripts of short poems of Robert Buchanan or [ Algernon Charles] Swinburne; encloses copy of "
    Birds
    . "]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to Jeanette Leonard Gilder, New York, 1882 Apr 20; ALS, 1 p.
    [Informs her that anything of his appearing in
    The Critic
    is at her and "the Critics" service.]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to Jeanette [Leonard] Gilder, New York, 1882 Aug 9; ALS, 1 p.
    [Recommends F. B. Stan[d]ford, a practiced writer who wrote reviews for
    The Independent
    . ]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, The Century, to Henry Mills Alden, New York, 1885 May 6; ALS, 1 p.
    [Wonders if Alden could use, and pay for, a poem by J. Hamstead, an elderly clergyman whose verse has been published gratis in the
    Evangelist
    thinks even more highly of his work that of [William Cullen] Bryant. ]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to Mr. [Rannan], 1894 May 22; ALS, 1 p.
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to Irving Bacheller, [ New York], 1895 Dec 15; ALS, 2 p.
    [Remarks about his poor eyesight, evident in his writing, which is difficult to decipher; discusses a paper of 1500-1800 words, which he sends to Bacheller.]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to [Livingston] Hopkins, 1899 Oct 30; ALS, 2 p.
    [Discusses his Japanese verse which appeared in Scribner; says he and his wife are pleased that Hopkins liked it.]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard to "Gentlemen", 1901 Feb 23; ALS, 1 p.
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, New York, to Jeanette [Leonard] Gilder, New York, [1881 May 2]; ALS, 1 p.
    [Includes date 1881 May 2 on verso.]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, [ New York], to Mrs. Terris, Dec 13; ALS, 2 p.
    [Says he has not acknowledged a call from Terris' daughter due to rheumatism in the right hand; tells her to get in touch with his publisher for a photo of him.]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard to unknown, n. d.; ALS, 2 p.
    [Fragment.]
  - Richard Henry Stoddard, [ New York], to Charles Goodrich Whiting, Springfield, Massachusetts, n .d.; ALS, 2 p.
- Miscellaneous
  - Custom House New York check for $83.33, Richard Henry Stoddard's salary as Debenture Clerk, 1856 May 31; Check
    [Endorsed by Stoddard.]
  - Receipt for $50.00 from Scribner & Co., 1874 Jun 1; Receipt
    [For article, "July Etchings"; signed by Richard Henry Stoddard. ]